<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The religious cavalier. Done out of French. By Gideon Pierreville, Gent.</title>
            <author>Pierreville, Gideon.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90699</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2212B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R181792</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077560</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077560</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151646</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90699)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151646)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2269:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The religious cavalier. Done out of French. By Gideon Pierreville, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Pierreville, Gideon.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 60, 51-108 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.H. for John Cripps, at the Black Lyon Post-Office, between the two Temple Gates in Fleetstreet.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library, Chicago, Illinois.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151646:1"/>
            <p>THE RELIGIOUS CAVALIER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Done out of French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Gideon Pierreville,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>John Cripps,</hi> at the <hi>Black Lyon</hi> Poſt-Office, between the two <hi>Temple Gates</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:151646:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151646:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable KATHARINE Counteſs of <hi>KILDAKE.</hi>
            </head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THE Ambition Writers have to flouriſh with ſome conſiderable perſonage in the Head of their Productions, would be leſs liable to Cenſure,
<pb facs="tcp:151646:3"/>if this Conduct of theirs were regulated by judgment, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluenced by good fortune. But we many times ſee the Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage they make Choice of, has no other deſert than that of a Glorious Title, nor no other Claim to their Eulogies than onely Eminent Extraction. But theſe addreſſes of mine how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever blame-worthy for their preſumption are at leaſt autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized by the Contemplation of ſuch Extraordinary Qualities as create a veneration in all mankind for your Ladiſhip, and have made me throng with this Offering to your Feet. My Deſign is onely, Madam, your
<pb facs="tcp:151646:3"/>Entertainment, which I thought this <hi>Religious Cavalier</hi> capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of affording, and that the merits of his Story would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him the honour of Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralization from your Ladiſhip's hands. I will leave to others, Madam, the vanity of endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to give the world an <hi>Idea</hi> of ſo charming a Character as that of your Ladiſhips; the vanity of pretending to draw and copy an Inimitable Beauty, and of proclaiming <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertues which can never be better expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed than by their effects, and which even out-ſhine the Glories of your Birth, and the luſtre of your alliance. All I aſpire to is
<pb facs="tcp:151646:4"/>the having one Voice in the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Conſort, and leave to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the profound reſpect and ſubmiſſion wherewith I am,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute> 
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Ladiſhips Moſt Humble and Moſt obedient Servant;</hi>
Gideon Pierreville.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151646:4"/>
            <head>THE RELIGIOUS CAVALIER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rope</hi> was in a Calm, <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Bellona</hi> weary of ſowing ſlaughter and horrour had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up to the delights of a ſedate and rural life one of their Braveſt Miniſters. A Nobleman did pleaſingly enjoy the ſatisfaction of the Vintage of the moſt delicious Wines of <hi>France,</hi> which grew near his Caſtle in the Province of <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne;</hi> when that Heaven thought fit to recompence his Heroick La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours by giving him in <hi>Placidia</hi> and <hi>Damis</hi> an accompliſht Daughter and a worthy Heir of his Great Heart:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151646:5"/>this laſt received an Education Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to his Extraction, and <hi>Placidia,</hi> who ſhared deepeſt in the inclination of her Parents, was brought up in all the Exerciſes of a perſon of her Rank. The Peace did not laſt long, ſome Bickerings ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing between <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> the Count, <hi>Placidia</hi>'s Father, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called to Court while ſhe took Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons upon the Lute and Guittar from an <hi>Italian</hi> Maſter who taught her to perfection the <hi>Italian</hi> Tongue, to which ſhe had a natural inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. That Illuſtrious Cavalier had order to march at the Head of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment to the Siege of <hi>Liſle,</hi> where having been wounded mortally by a <hi>Granado,</hi> he found in the Ditch of that Town the uſual Tomb of Great Men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Placidia</hi> was then but twelve years old, when the Counteſs her Mother received news of the Death of her Illuſtrious Husband. That
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151646:5"/>Lady imparted the ſad tidings to her Daughter of the tragical end of the Count her Father, who though in ſo tender an age had nevertheleſs ſenſe enough to be infinitely grieved for the loſs: they both afforded for ſome time Tears to the Memory of the Deceaſed, which were ſtill trick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling when the Counteſs took an Oath uſual to young Widows, never to think of a ſecond Marriage.</p>
            <p>They mourn'd for a ſeaſon in the Countrey, where all the Nobility came to Court to them, as to the Principal Family of the Province. <hi>Placidia</hi> being lookt upon as a rich Match had many Votaries, but as ſhe was not onely yet too young, the Counteſs her Mother fancied ſhe could no where ſo well receive the Breeding of a perſon of her Quality as at <hi>Paris,</hi> which we may call the School of politeneſs. Whereupon ſhe took a reſolution of going to ſpend the Winter there; and ſome
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151646:6"/>few days after, going thither accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, ſhe took a Houſe ready fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in the <hi>Fauxbourg de Saint Germain,</hi> which is the part of the Town moſt frequented by Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers who live at a great rate. The Counteſs made ſo great a figure, and <hi>Placidia</hi> was ſo beautifull as to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract to their Lodging many gallant Men. Their Houſe became in a few months the Rendevous of an infinity of Courtiers, who perſuaded the Counteſs to allow of Gaming at her Lodgings. She was of too great Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to give occaſion to any ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſelf-intereſt and libertiniſm. It ſeems as if perſons who are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by their Extraction are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of giving of themſelves any low ſentiments, and it is commonly onely thoſe who have neither much good nor ill fortune that Calumny attacks.</p>
            <p>Amongſt that Crowd of young Sparks, who paid Viſits of Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151646:6"/>to the Counteſs, and aſſiduities to the blooming Charms of <hi>Placidia,</hi> two Cavaliers diſtinguiſht them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves amongſt the reſt, inſomuch that it ſeem'd as if Colonel <hi>Fragel</hi> and the Marquis <hi>de Phare,</hi> were born, the one as the older of the two for the Counteſs, and the other for the Daughter, though indeed the Colonel and the Marquis had onely Eyes for <hi>Placidia.</hi> The Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the genius of thoſe two Gentlemen was very different: the Colonel was a man naturally reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and did not, like the Marquiſs, take a pride in proclaiming himſelf the Favourite of <hi>Placidia</hi> though he really was ſo: the Marquis on the contrary gloried in being thought the Lover of ſo beautifull a perſon; and that all the world might flatter him with ſo fine a Conqueſt, he let no opportunity eſcape of promoting the Opinion of his being her Gallant. He went neither to the Play-houſe,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151646:7"/>Park, nor any other publick place, but in her Coach; he never ſtirred from her Houſe, and was always making her ſome conſiderable Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, which ſhe accepted by her Mothers leave, who would not have been ſorry that a Young Man of that Quality were entred into her alliance. The Colonel for his part being very much perſuaded, that how favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoever <hi>Placidia</hi>'s might be to the Marquis her Heart belied her Eyes, and her complaiſance did husband his addreſſes to her with ſo much art and nicety, that he became the onely object of her tender Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. He had indeed a Rival in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, but was convinced <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidia</hi> had for that concurrent no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing beyond indifferency.</p>
            <p>The Marquis having much of the indiſcretion of the age, and reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the kind looks of his pretended Miſtreſs as certain Favours, having contracted ſome acquaintance at the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151646:7"/>Counteſs's Houſe with the Colonel, who came thither every Evening, did without much ſcrutiny engage ſo far in friendſhip with him, as to make him the Confident of all his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets. Their commerce of friendſhip was encreaſed by Parties of Divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which they made together; the Colonel appearing indifferent to the Marquis in all that concerned <hi>Placidia:</hi> the Marquis did not think he ran any riſque by unboſoming to him his diſpoſition for that lovely perſon. The Colonel, who was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably perfect in the art of diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, did outwardly eſpouſe his Cauſe, flattered him more and more with his having inſinuated himſelf into his Miſtreſs's heart, and made uſe of his weak ſide to promote his own affairs. And indeed the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, whom her Daughter and the Marquis had prepoſſeſſed with the good intentions of the Colonel, did willingly admit of his entring into
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151646:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:151646:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151646:9"/>ſomething private Converſations with <hi>Placidia;</hi> at his coming from which, the Colonel made the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis a deſcription of ſo tender a love, that this Cavalier fancied him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf paſſionately beloved. In the mean while the Colonel took ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the liberty that was granted him of approaching <hi>Placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia.</hi> He found the ſecret to ſurprize that young Heart, whereof he ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred himſelf ſo abſolutely the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that that Divine Creature onely acted by him, and had no more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than thoſe he inſpired into her: the little inclination the Counteſs had for the Colonel, at leaſt in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of all alliance, was ſufficiently known by our two Lovers.</p>
            <p>They vowed to one another an Eternal Fidelity, being reſolved to wait a ſeaſonable opportunity, and contrived the means together of making a property of the Marquis's eaſineſs, and of diverting themſelves
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151646:9"/>at his Coſt. It was but too eaſie for them to render him their laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-ſtock, and the ſubject of their paſtime, he went very open to <hi>Placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> and concealed nothing from the Colonel.</p>
            <p>Some years paſſed in this inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Commerce for the one, though not ſo for the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Placidia</hi> with age became more cautious and rational, when Love, who is always the Authour of ſome diſorder, and glories in keeping to himſelf the Subjects he has once ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued to his Empire, came to diſturb the pleaſures our Lovers had hardly taſted. A Member of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who though a Gown-man, was not the leſs amourouſly inclin'd, frequented the Counteſs's Houſe, and had for ſome months made Love to her; when time and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion had worn out of the memory of that beautifull Widow the Oath ſhe had taken, if for his part he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151646:10"/>made known to her his pasſion, ſhe for hers did not prove inſenſible. A little thing does revive thoſe flames that are newly extinguiſhed; the delights that are enjoyed in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred bond of Marriage did renew their traces in the Counteſs's imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: The Gallant did ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully promote the recalling of thoſe tickling <hi>Idea's,</hi> that theirs would not have been deferred, ſo vehement was their reciprocal paſſion, if her Lover had not repreſented to her, that it was firſt of all convenient to ſecure themſelves from the inſults of the Family by giving an account of <hi>Damis</hi> and <hi>Placidia</hi>'s Eſtate, whoſe Guardian ſhe had been. He could have wiſh'd he might have rid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of them both, by confining them to a Cloiſter; but <hi>Damis</hi> being the onely Heir of his Father's Name, it was neceſſary he ſhould continue in the world; and this made them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to employ their Friends to have
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151646:10"/>him received as one of the King's Pages. They did not think <hi>Placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> ſo neceſſary a Moveable in the world, how beautifull ſoever ſhe was in her Curls, they thought a Nuns dreſs would not unbecome her; whereupon they condemned her to the obſcurities of a Cloiſter with precipitation, and conferred afterwards ſeriouſly of the means to make her deſirous of a Monaſtical life.</p>
            <p>The Deceaſed Earl had a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Siſter in the Convent of <hi>Avenay,</hi> ſome Leagues from the City of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> and very near his Caſtle. The Counteſs's Gallant thought that Sanctuary very worthy of <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidia</hi>'s Vows, and told the Counteſs that without ſounding her upon the buſineſs, it was requiſite to ſteal her away from the ſight of her Adorers, and under a pretext of a return, carry her to the Caſtle, and from thence cunningly deliver her to her
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151646:11"/>Aunt. This Reſolution was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly taken, and the Gallant ſtaid at <hi>Paris</hi> to ſolicit for a conſiderable Place, and likewiſe that he might not be thought to have had any hand in the matter, while the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs took all the exacteſt meaſures poſſible for the execution of her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Placidia,</hi> who had not had the leaſt hint of all theſe contrivances, was extremely ſurprized that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having the time to take her leave of any body, ſhe ſaw her ſelf obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to take Coach with her Mother, who told her ſhe took that courſe to avoid the importunate civility of the taking leave of a hundred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who would have come to ſee them. Whereupon they took the Road to <hi>Rhemes</hi> in order to their going to their own Caſtle, when the Colonel, whom they had not ſeen in two days, and who had had notice of their ſudden departure
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151646:11"/>met them as returning Poſt from <hi>Louvoy</hi> for particular affairs. The Counteſs fearing if ſhe ſhould flatter him with a ſpeedy return, it would engage him to wait on them to the Caſtle, told the Colonel that ſome Domeſtick affairs called her for a fortnight to her Houſe, and that about that time her Daughter and ſhe ſhould be returned to <hi>Paris.</hi> This Cavalier took this ſpecious rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for a real truth, and offered with ſo good a Grace to guard them at leaſt as far as the Caſtle, that this favour could not be refuſed him: whereupon he diſmiſſed his Poſtboy, and took place in the Coach, where he was ſo much maſter of his Eyes, that it was impoſſible the Counteſs ſhould perceive they kept any cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with thoſe of <hi>Placidia</hi>'s. At their coming to the Caſtle, the Counteſs being taken up with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewing her Houſe, the Colonel had the opportunity to take a turn in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151646:12"/>Garden with <hi>Placidia,</hi> going from Walk to Walk they at length came to an Alley that was ſhaded and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with Trees, and where no body could ſee or overhear them; they ſeated themſelves, and began to make the moſt tender declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons imaginable, and renew their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Oaths of an inviolable fidelity, when the diſcovery of a Footman's coming ſlowly to them, interrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Conversation, and oblig'd them to go partake of a Collation. During all the Evening, and the next Morning untill eleven a clock that the Colonel departed, our Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Lovers had neither time nor opportunity to converſe, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther undeſignedly proving to them a troubleſome <hi>Argus.</hi> But what do not Lovers ſay when they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to hold their peace, and what is more pathetical and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive than their ſilence? Before the Colonel took Horſe, he told <hi>Placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151646:12"/>after a gallant manner in her Mothers preſence, <hi>Well! Queen of Beauties, when will the Marquis have the pleaſure of ſeeing you again?</hi> whereto that innocent Victim re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied ingenuouſly, <hi>My Mother gives me hopes it will be within fifteen days. That time will not be over long if it be the term of your return,</hi> reaſſumed he, <hi>But if your abſence, fair</hi> Placidia, <hi>ſhould laſt fifty days it would be uneaſie to you, and a mortification to your Lovers.</hi> On the morrow the Counteſs propoſed to her Daughter to go make a Viſit to her Religious Aunt: Never having ſeen her, ſhe ſeemed very deſirous to accompany her Mother to the Convent. Immediately after their arrival there, the Aunt came into the Parlour, where after ſome ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly converſation the diſcourſe became more free, at the end whereof our Ladies were invited to a Collation which was prepared for them in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Parlour. The good humour
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151646:13"/>of both ſides the Grate did partake in the Entertainment, from which the Counteſs got up to diſcourſe her Religious Siſter-in-law upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign ſhe had upon her Daughter. That voluntary Captive, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Cloiſter Maximes look'd upon the moſt innocent plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the age as forbidden fruit, did applaud the Counteſs's Dectara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and promiſed her to doe all that was poſſible to prevail with <hi>Placidia</hi> to give her Mother the ſatisfaction ſhe expected from her ſubmiſſion. There remained now nothing more than to make the Daughter deſirous to ſee the innerſide of the Convent, and to make her reſolve to ſpend ſome days there. The Nuns are but too ingenious at inſpiring ſuch kind of inclinations: they propoſed the matter ſo cunningly to the innocent <hi>Placidia,</hi> that the Doors were not ſoon enough open. This Religious Houſe being one of the fineſt of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151646:13"/>Province, upon the firſt propoſition that was made to <hi>Placidia</hi> of ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome days there ſhe accepted the offer, and conſented to ſtay a week; whereupon in ſhe went, and her Mother having paſs'd her word to ſend for her back at the time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſhe took Coach and return'd to the Caſtle. The honeſt Nun in the mean while did dexterouſly try how her Niece ſtood affected, and made her ſuch fine deſcriptions of a retired life, that if ſhe had not a natural horrour for ſolitude ſhe would have immediately complied and deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Veil. As ſhe had not the leaſt diſpoſition to a retired life, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the facetiouſneſs of her gay humour, ſhe did but make a jeſt on't when they propoſed her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the world: Her free reper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees which pall'd thoſe who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to reduce her, did not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the Aunt, who daily ſeem'd to inſinuate to her that the Counteſs
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151646:14"/>her Siſter-in-law had onely left her with her that ſhe might reliſh the pleaſure of a Cloiſter-life, and how eaſie it was to attain Heaven in that retreat. This old piece of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency one day ſeeing that all thoſe rich Images ſhe laid before her Nieces eyes ſeem'd to her hideous, and that ſhe ſeem'd to be extremely diſguſted with the little ſhe had taſted of a Monaſtical life, full of an indiſcreet zeal, ſhe told her, <hi>My dear Niece, I muſt at preſent open my heart to you, and declare what is abſolutely the will of your Lady Mother. What is her will,</hi> interrupted <hi>Placidia</hi> laughing, <hi>is it that I change my Hood into a Veil? Yes,</hi> replied the Aunt gravely, <hi>and ſhe brought you hither for no other purpoſe. Placidia</hi> who thought it was onely a trick to try her made anſwer after a drolling way, that ſhe was yet too young, and uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of judging of the conſequences of a choice of that importance; that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151646:14"/>ſhe would take time to think of it, and that if Heaven inſpired her with a love of ſolitude ſhe did aſſure her that ſhe was ſo well pleas'd with their Convent as that ſhe ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it before any other. The old one continued ſtill to inſiſt, and <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidia</hi> to defend her ſelf, till the next day when ſhe expected a Coach to fetch her home, ſhe was much ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized to ſee a Servant of her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers enter the Court with a Cart laden with all manner of things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the furniſhing a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber neatly: As ſoon as the Servant ſaw her, he came up and delivered her this Letter from the Counteſs.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I do not doubt, my deareſt Daughter, but that the Convent of <hi>Avenay</hi> does pleaſe you extremely, and that it will be joyfull news to you that Heaven deſtins you for that place: your Aunt will have informed you of my good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, liſten to the voice of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151646:15"/>ſpirit which calls you in ſecret, let not thoſe holy ardours cool in your heart, and be aſſured that being a good Mother, there ſhall be nothing wanting on my part for your ſpending a calm and happy life in the land of the Saints, where you are at preſent. I ſend you wherewith to furniſh your Chamber; your Aunt will take care to provide you with all the other little things you ſhall have occaſion for. Be carefull to write to me from time to time, and be perſuaded that I ſhall ever be your beſt friend.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Placidia</hi> was ſeiz'd at the reading of this Letter with ſo great an aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, that ſhe had like to have fallen into a ſwoon; nevertheleſs ſhe made a great effort upon her ſelf, and ſurpaſſing the ſentiments of her age, ſhe turn'd towards her Aunt, and told her with tears in her Eyes, <hi>I perceive, reverend Mother, I muſt be ſacrificed to Family-intereſts, by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151646:15"/>burying me all alive in a place, where for want of calling, I can never take delight in; but no matter, no matter; God the revenger of oppreſſed innocence, will free me out of the Captivity I am brought under by a criminal ſelf-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. I conſent to ſtay here till the Divine Providence ſhall otherwiſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it.</hi> They unloaded the Cart, and <hi>Placidia</hi> ſent back the Coach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man without giving him any anſwer for the Counteſs her Mother.</p>
            <p>All the Nuns, as ſoon as he was departed, aſſembled round <hi>Placidia,</hi> aſſured her of their good will, and ſtrove who ſhould give her the moſt diverſion. She ſupported her ſelf in that tribulation untill the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, when grief got ſo much the upper hand of her, that it caſt her into a languiſhment, which was followed by a Fever that laſted above four months.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:151646:16"/>
            <p>In the mean while the Counteſs return'd to <hi>Paris,</hi> gave an account to her Lover, who had gotten a conſiderable Place at Court, of what had paſs'd, and told him ſhe believ'd Heaven conſpir'd with them, and that her Daughter was really born for a Cloiſter-life. This Gallant, upon this teſtimony looking upon <hi>Placidia</hi>'s having profeſſed her ſelf a Nun as a thing certain, repreſented to the Counteſs that nothing hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred their Marriage, to which he found that fair Widow ſo ready diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that the Nuptial Ceremonies were completed, and the Marriage conſummated. She had changed her Lodgings, and having taken the Houſe of her new Husband in the Street called <hi>Richlieu,</hi> ſhe went eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day to Maſs to a Convent hard by; the Colonel being one day there, was extremely ſurprized to ſee the Counteſs, whom he hardly knew again, for that ſhe had chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151646:16"/>her Mourning into Cloth of Gold. He approach'd one of her <hi>Lacquayes</hi> who wore her Husband's Livery, and inquired of him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being perceived by the Lady, after the health of <hi>Mademoiſelle Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidia,</hi> and after the place where ſhe was. The Footman not having been forewarned, made preſently anſwer, that they had left her ſick in the Convent of <hi>Avenay,</hi> where ſhe did not ſeem to be overwell pleaſed. The undiſcreet eaſineſs of this Fellow, making the Colonel pry farther into the buſineſs, he was inform'd of the Counteſs's alliance with the Courtier, and the place of their abode. Having heard too much for his repoſe, he withdrew in a penſive humour, and went directly to his own Houſe for the taking Reſolutions there becoming the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity of his Love.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:151646:17"/>
            <p>In a moment he form'd the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of taking Poſt to go to <hi>Avenay</hi> in all haſte; he arrived there the next morning. He asked for <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle Placidia</hi> at the Grate, who came thither all languiſhing as ſhe was in the company of an old Matron, according to the Cloiſter cuſtome. After ſome words purely of civility, that poor Lover told his dear inclinations, with an air which bore the character of indifferency. <hi>Well,</hi> Mademoiſelle, <hi>the Divine Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is willing to have you of the number of his well beloved Spouſes. Since when have you received ſuch ſalutary inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations? truly the conduct of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is admirable upon the Elect. I cannot ſufficiently admire how that in ſo ſhort a time a perſon could be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with to leave the Court for a Deſart, and ſuch a perſon as ſeem'd naturally inclin'd to the ſplendour of the world. I can hardly conceive the force of the motions that have prompted
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151646:17"/>you to come bury your ſelf all alive in a Houſe, which nevertheleſs we may with juſtice call the Temple of Vertue.</hi> He would ſtill have continued his witty deſcant upon this Point, had not <hi>Placidia,</hi> who feared he would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly paſs on to ſome matter which might have given ſuſpicion to her old Companion, interrupted him with a ſigh, and ſaid, <hi>That in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed her Call had ſomething impure, that ſhe held it from a ſecret intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her Mothers, who had by arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice got her into the Cloiſter; but that God who commonly makes uſe of the ſelf-intereſted deſigns of men for the working his will, made her daily more and more paſſionate for a Religious life, for which ſhe had then as much inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as ſhe had in the beginning hated its Maximes.</hi> Our Cavalier, partly gueſſing at the reaſon ſhe thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed her ſentiments, made a ſhew as if he had the ſame ſenſe too. He began to make a hideous deſcription
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151646:18"/>of the Age, and to extoll the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of a retired life with ſo much eloquence, as to ſay he himſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to die in a Convent, that the old Nun was diſpoſed to leave them at liberty. And truly that zealous Old one hearing him diſcourſe after ſo religious a manner, fancied this Gentleman was the perſon who had married the Counteſs, and that he came thither onely to inflame <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidia</hi>'s paſſion for the Veil. Poſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with this opinion, ſhe thought convenient to leave them alone to converſe together, and retired un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretext of ſome regular exerciſe which demanded her appearance in the Dormitory. She was no ſooner out of the Parlour than that <hi>Placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi>'s Lover ſeemed quite ſtruck dumb, and ſhe for her part could not ſpeak to him a word. They look'd upon one another for ſome time without ſpeaking, the Eyes alone being the faithfull Interpreters
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151646:18"/>of the diſpoſition of their Hearts. <hi>Placidia</hi>'s fears gave liberty to their mutual grief. She related to her Lover the procedure and ill deſigns of her Mother, and conjured him to believe that ſhe had hot any incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for a retired life, though ſhe outwardly ſeem'd to have for the obtaining the liberty of the Parlour which otherwiſe ſhe would have been deprived of. Upon this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration our Cavalier told <hi>Placidia</hi> with ſuch a tone of voice as inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to her the ſtate of his paſſion. <hi>Do you then ſtill love me, charming</hi> Placidia? <hi>may I preſume that the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of the world has not been capable to break thoſe ties that Heaven has join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Yon ought to be perſuaded,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied ſhe, <hi>that I love you, and that what violences ſoever I may be made to ſuffer, they ſhall never raviſh from me a liberty which I have engaged to you, and which if you do not enjoy, you your ſelf ſhall be onely to blame.</hi> Her tears
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151646:19"/>ſtifled the reſt, and excited thoſe of the Cavalier, who was little accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to ſhed any. Nevertheleſs they held up at length, and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier renewing the diſcourſe, ſaid to <hi>Placidia, What can I doe, my dear</hi> Demoiſelle, <hi>in the preſent conjuncture? Command, I am ready to undertake all things to the prejudice of my Intereſts, of my glory, and of my life. Continue to love,</hi> reſum'd ſhe, <hi>and that is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient. The advice you give me,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Colonel hereupon, <hi>is injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to my fidelity. I have made a vow to love you eternally, and I do not believe that death can be capable of deſtroying my inviolable paſſion. Does the buſineſs lie in hazarding my eſtate, my employments, my honour and my life for the freeing you out of pain, I am ready to expoſe all, and even to ſacrifice my ſelf for your ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction? Placidia</hi> ſeem'd to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded that her Lover ſpoke ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when ſhe made him anſwer, <hi>That
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151646:19"/>it was not yet time to come to extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, that they were to wait the iſſue of things, that perhaps Heaven chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging her Mothers heart, would reſtore them to one another without their being obliged to run any hazard:</hi> ſhe added, <hi>that without doubt ſhe ſhould be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to take the Veil, but in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terval between the taking the Habit and the Profeſſion they might take mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and contrive her eſcape if it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came neceſſary.</hi> The Colonel, who was juſt a going into the Campagne, and had laid out all his money for the putting himſelf in a fine equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page, what inclination ſoever he had for <hi>Placidia</hi>'s freedom, yet had not ſo much forgot his obligations, and his duty, but that he was glad to ſee her diſpoſed to take patience for ſome time. He engaged his Faith for all ſhe had a mind to, and took his leave of her, after having paſſed his word to come and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her in a ſhort time.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:151646:20"/>
            <p>He was no ſooner returned to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> than that he met with the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis,</hi> more paſſionate than ever for <hi>Placidia,</hi> whom he had been newly informed was detain'd by her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers command, in the Abbey of the Benedictine Nuns at <hi>Avenay.</hi> This young man having invited him to Supper, they went together into the Balcony, when all their diſcourſe was of <hi>Placidia</hi>'s abſence. <hi>I ſhall know the end of the Intrigue,</hi> ſaid the Marquis, <hi>I have ſpies abroad, and my</hi> Valet de Chambre, <hi>a cunning fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, has already got the length of the foot of one of the Counteſs's Domeſticks, who has already told him ſeveral things. I ſhall he revenged, on that unnatural Woman, and at the peril of my life, I will free that adorable Creature from ſo diſagreeable way of living: I intend to go Poſt three days hence to the place where ſhe is, and I ſhall he informed from her her ſelf what deſigns they have upon her: If you will be of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151646:20"/>Party, I offer to be at the charges of the Journey, and to ſpare nothing for your good diverſion.</hi> The Colonel pretending ſome buſineſs which tied him indiſpenſably to the Court, told him that he would not adviſe him to undertake that Journey, and that undoubtedly the Mother, who had cauſed her Daughter to be confined, would have ſo much wit as to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid ſhe ſhould have the freedom of the Grate, and that thus he might, perhaps, go very far to ſeek in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal a greater matter of vexation. This remonſtrance of the Nun did but irritate the Marquis's paſſion, who bethought himſelf at that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant of an expedient which prov'd ſucceſsfull. <hi>I will carry a Coat to be made like the Counteſs's Livery,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>and I do not doubt but that ſuch a Caſaque will procure me entrance into the Parlour.</hi> This was the onely expedient he could employ, that his deſign might have a favourable iſſue.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151646:21"/>He executed what he had concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and under that diſguiſe he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a private conference with <hi>Placidia,</hi> though the Abbeſs had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived order but two days before not to ſuffer her to ſpeak to any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, upon the notice the Counteſs had had that a Cavalier had been to make a Viſit to her Daughter; but ſhe could not nevertheleſs diſcover who he was by the imperfect de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription that had been ſent her of the perſon. The Abbeſs, not in the leaſt doubting but that this preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Servant was a Domeſtick of the Counteſs's Family, allowed <hi>Placidia</hi> to ſee and ſtay ſome time with him.</p>
            <p>That charming perſon knew him immediately under that borrowed Habit, and like to thoſe who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drowning ſeize on all thoſe they meet with, ſhe made Careſſes to that traveſtied Cavalier, in hopes, that if the Colonel happened to fail
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151646:21"/>in his word, ſhe might make uſe of the miniſtry of this Spark for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of her liberty. It is not to be conceived how much the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis's paſſion was encreaſed by this Interview; he ſpoke of nothing but of carrying her away at that very time, and would have puſht on his indiſcretion much farther, if <hi>Placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> had not checked his furious fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, by remonſtrating to him, that precipitation in a buſineſs of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was rather capable of ſpoiling things, than to procure them ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs according to their deſire. That Illuſtrious Captive knew ſo well how to curb the boiling temper of the young Cavalier, that ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared him for all ſhe had a mind to. They took together the ſame Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions that ſhe had taken with the Colonel, that is to ſay, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected her eſcape m caſe the iſſue of things conſtrained them to that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity. This Conference which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151646:22"/>would have laſted much longer, was interrupted by the coming in of the Abbeſs, who inquired of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of the Counteſs's health. He underſtood himſelf well enough to ſatisfie exactly to all her demands, and had likewiſe a moments time to diſcourſe <hi>Placidia,</hi> whom Supper deprived him of, after having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from her a thouſand proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of an immortal fidelity.</p>
            <p>This traveſtied Lover having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Poſt again, in a few hours ſpace got to <hi>Paris,</hi> where impatient to impart to the Colonel the ſucceſs of his Voyage, he ſought for him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after his arrival but ſought for him; in vain; that Officer had received Orders the Evening before to goe inceſſantly to his Regiment at <hi>Peronne,</hi> for to march elſewhere. The young Marquis, who had not yet made a Campagne, and who had made his intereſt at Court for a Troup of Horſe obtained that very
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151646:22"/>day the Commiſſion, with Orders to go join the Troups near: St. <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin.</hi> This new Dignity did a little deface out of his mind the <hi>Ideas</hi> of <hi>Placidia,</hi> and inſtead thereof, traced the image of glory, which made him depart at that very inſtant.</p>
            <p>In the Neighbourhood of <hi>Arras</hi> was the Rendeſvouz of the whole Army deſigned for <hi>Flanders.</hi> Our young Captain met there with, the Colonel, <hi>Placidia</hi>'s Lover, to whom he gave an account of what had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed between him and his Miſtreſs, and of the deſign he had to procure her Eſcape, at his return, from the Campagne, if they forced her to make her Vows. The Colonel, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending that the boiling youth of this Officer might prevent his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, contracted with him a greater commerce of Friendſhip, and: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiny would have it that they often made uſe of the ſame Ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>ir Regiments never ſeparating. The
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151646:23"/>Campagne was ſevere, and gave not any repoſe to thoſe Military Sparks, who had no ſooner began to reliſh the refreſhments of the Winter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarters than the Marquis's paſſion was ſo reinflamed, that he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in his mouth but the lovely name of <hi>Placidia.</hi> Our Colonel perceiving that this paſſion degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated into fury, and fearing it might make him attempt ſomething to the prejudice of his own, beſides foreſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that this young man was upon the point of obtaining three months leave, which he ſolicited for the going to ſee <hi>Placidia,</hi> he fell out with him upon a poſitive diſpute that happened at play. He had alſo an inclination to rid himſelf of this raſh Rival, and for that purpoſe Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged him to meet him half a league from <hi>Peronne.</hi> The Mine was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; they were betrayed by one of their Seconds, inſomuch that they were taken into Cuſtody when
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151646:23"/>they were upon the point of fighting, and by his Majeſtie's Order confined at <hi>Peronne.</hi> They ſtayed there near two months, where they had time enough to be reconciled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Placidia</hi> was in the mean while clothed with the Habit of the Novi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the time of her Profeſſion grew near, which caſt her into a mortal ſadneſs, and her grief did with ſo much the more reaſon aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in that ſhe received no tidings of her Lovers. When that our two Cavaliers were ſet at liberty, the young Officer obtained ſix weeks leave for to go ſettle ſome affairs, but he deſtined it for the going to give <hi>Placidia</hi> aſſurances of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of his flames. The Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, whoſe paſſion was no leſs ſtrong to go ſee the worthy object of his Love, infinitely troubled to ſee that this young Man prevented him in a Viſit, which he had for above a year projected to pay <hi>Placidia,</hi> did not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151646:24"/>however ſhew the leaſt concern to his Rival, and onely conjured him To preſent his humble Service to that charming Priſoner. The Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Coat, whereof we have already made mention, did the Marquis one good Office more: It gave him a free acceſs to the beautifull Novice, to whom, in the ſeveral Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they had had together, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpoke of the Colonel, but as of a Man who had for a long time been confiſcated into the Chirurgeons hands for the cure of a ſhamefull Diſeaſe. He enjoyed the Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that illuſtrious Captive for above fifteen days, always pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Counteſs being, at the Caſtle, did ſtill give him in charge ſome new Commiſſion for her Daughter, at the end of which time fearing to give ſome occaſion of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt, he took leave of <hi>Placidia,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having engaged by inviolable Oaths to ſteal her away though ſhe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151646:24"/>were profeſſed Religious of twenty years ſtanding. The impatience he was in made him return with all ſpeed to his Quarters, where he did not find the Colonel, whom with grief he heard was gone to <hi>Paris.</hi> But as he did not think him his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, his abſence did not oblige him to entertain any ſuch ſuſpicion, as to oblige him to quit his Poſt; but he impatiently expected the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel's return.</p>
            <p>The Colonel having never been but once at the Grate, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded that he could not be known by any of the Nuns, ſent word to the Abbeſs, that the Governour of his Majeſtie's Pages, who had Siſter <hi>Placidia</hi>'s Brother under his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, did on purpoſe alight there to make her a Viſit, and that being very much in haſte, he deſired my Lady Superiour to have the goodneſs to allow him to pay her and Siſter <hi>Placidia</hi> his reſpects Our beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151646:25"/>Novice was then walking with the Abbeſs in the Garden, her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhip having taken Phyſick that day, when that Siſter <hi>Touriere</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſted her. This good natur'd Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſs being indiſpoſed, and ſeeing <hi>Placidia</hi> juſt ready to make her Vows, would not deprive her of this ſlight ſatisfaction. She ſent her to the Parlour, charging her to pay her civilities, and make her excuſes to this Gentleman, and aſſigned her the Sub-prioreſs for a Companion. Our cunning Cavalier imagining that ſhe would not come alone to the Parlour, had taken his meaſures, and had written a Letter for to. ſlip into <hi>Placidia</hi>'s hand, wherein he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted her with the true diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Heart, and his ſincere ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Placidia</hi> conjecturing by the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity which the Colonel affected, that he was not willing to be known, ſeem'd very indifferent at his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151646:25"/>and hardly rais'd her eyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. A ſecret joy rendring her mute, the Sub-prioreſs, who took her ſilence for an effect: of her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, entertained the Cavalier, whoſe diſcourſe was ſuited to her circumſtances. This diſcreet Lover did not ſhew any motion of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience he was in to entertain <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidia</hi> in private, who for her part did not in the leaſt make appear how deſirous ſhe was of a particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. The old and troubleſome Confident after an hours diſcourſe got up, having told the Novice that it was time to retire. She was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to obey, and all that ſhe could doe was, in drawing the Curtain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Grate to receive ſubtly her Lover's Letter, which contained what follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I am always the ſame, lovely <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidia,</hi> and though you ſhould ceaſe to love me, I could not reſolve to change.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151646:26"/>Let what will happen you are not bound to be eternally unhappy, or fate ſhall involve me in the ſame misfortune. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey ſtill for ſome time the caprichiouſneſs of Deſtiny; you will ſuddenly triumph over its malice, and will find the calm is very pleaſing when it is uſher'd in by a tempeſt. Your Captivity is near its period, venture all for all. Do not fear that new Vows can weaken your firſt Promiſes. The God who knows that you have given me your ſaith in exchange with mine, does be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand diſcharge you from the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of Promiſes which the inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and paſſion of a Mother will force you perhaps to make. There is great talk of a Peace, but whether according to the good pleaſure of God the King will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow it upon <hi>Europe,</hi> or that the War continues, I will take ſuch a courſe that in the midſt of a general trouble we will enjoy the delights of a ſedate life. You may promiſe your ſelf that in a ſhort time you will recover your liberty,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151646:26"/>or at leaſt will ſee the moſt faithfull of all Lovers periſh in this Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The reading of this Letter did ſomething pacifie <hi>Placidia</hi>'s mind, who was very deſirous to have had a particular Converſation with her dear Colonel. He had promiſed her before parting, that at his return from the Caſtle of <hi>Syllery,</hi> whither he was going, he would come-take the Letter which ſhe was deſirous to write to her Brother; an expedient which he had on purpoſe invented that ſhe might have time to make him an Anſwer. And indeed ſhe made him a very kind one, which ſhe ſlipt into his hand inſtead of the Letter which with the Abbeſs's leave ſhe wrote to her Brother. He had no ſooner received it than that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to be very much in haſte, he took his leave of <hi>Placidia</hi> and her too faithfull Companion. You
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151646:27"/>may eaſily imagine he did not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it ſealed up to his Garriſon. A paſſionate love is always impatient. Now to reade this pretious Letter with all the attention which its mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deſerved, twenty paces from the Village he alighted from his Horſe, which he tied to a Tree, and after having kiſſed the Interpreter of <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidia</hi>'s ſentiments, he read this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter two or three times, its Contents being as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Would to God, my dear Colonel, that you were as invulnerable as you are faithfull to me, I ſhould not then live thus in mortal apprehenſions: there is not an hour either day or night hut that I figure to my ſelf that you are brought back to your Tent full of a hundred glorious wounds. A true Lover ought to be ſomething a Coward: Pardon me for inſpiring into you ſuch baſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents. I am willing that you ſhould follow the impetuoſity of your great
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151646:27"/>heart, but I would willingly run with you to glory, and fall under the ſame blow. You promiſe me my freedom: If it is at preſent in your power, who will be ſecurity that the tragical end of Heroes with which you are threatned will not to morrow ruine your good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions? Steal from glory what you are owing to Love, and be aſſured that there is nothing but your abſence that renders me unhappy.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter very much mov'd our Cavalier, and made him make reflexions which caſt him into ſome trouble. <hi>Placidia</hi> being got into the Belfrey of the Church to follow him with her eyes as far as her ſight could bear, obſerved that in his <hi>reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie,</hi> he turned his eyes above twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty times towards the place from whence he came, which ſhewed that he did not part from her but with extreme regret. He returned to <hi>Peronne,</hi> went to his Quarters,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151646:28"/>where he impatiently expected the Spring, when that charming ſeaſon calls to Arms. The Marquis lived in very good underſtanding with him, and was always diſcourſing him of <hi>Placidia,</hi> of the return of whoſe paſſion he flattered himſelf with very little reaſon. The Army in the midſt of <hi>March</hi> marched into <hi>Flanders</hi> and deprived our Lovers both of their hopes, and convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of ſeeing again, ſo ſoon as they could have wiſhed, the perſon by whom they were ſo diverſly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Placidia,</hi> whoſe year of <hi>Novici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate</hi> being revolved, and having given her ſelf up as a prey to her profound ſadneſs, becauſe that ſhe did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any news of her Lovers, made a vertue of neceſſity: and animating her ſelf ſtill with couragious hopes, conſented to make her Vows. Her Father-in-law and the Counteſs her Mother came to make her a Viſit a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151646:28"/>fortnight before the Profeſſion, to whom ſhe teſtified an extraordinary inclination for a Religious life. They applauded her Reſolution, and gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all ſhe demanded of her Father's Eſtate for the rendring her recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the more pompous, even to the giving her to the value of two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crowns in Jewels, which ſhe ſaid was to be employed for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Ornaments of the Altar, but which ſhe never parted with. Nothing was wanting of all that could render the Ceremony the more ſolemn: the Mother had brought with her an Abbot from <hi>Paris,</hi> a very eloquent man, who made a Diſcourſe very ſuitable to the occaſion, and in whoſe hands <hi>Placidia</hi> made her Vows. All theſe paſs'd without the knowledge of that lovely Maids Lovers, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs did expect this unvolun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Sacrifice. The War being more than ever re-inflamed, his Majeſty
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151646:29"/>made an expreſs prohibition upon pain of being Caſhiered from the ſervice to all Officers of what quality ſoever they were, not to quit the Garriſon upon any pretext, and this prohibition ſubſiſted during two Winter Quarters conſecutively; for which reaſon neither the Marquis nor the Colonel durſt for two years budge from their Regiments to go comfort the poor <hi>Placidia,</hi> who ſhed every night a torrent of tears upon the remembrance of the Colonel her Lover. And indeed ſhe could not perſuade her ſelf any thing elſe, than that he and the Marquis had loſt their lives, ſince after ſuch ſtrong promiſes they kept ſo obſtinate a ſilence. As ſhe was one day con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring with one of her moſt inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Friends, of thoſe who had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly an eſteem for her, ſhe ſpoke of the Colonel whom ſhe imagined was kind, and the knowledge of whoſe Deſtiny ſhe would have pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151646:29"/>with half her life. This Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident not wanting wit, though ſhe had been from her infancy in the Cloiſter, remonſtrated to her that it was very eaſie to know what was become of him, and that there nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded no more than to write directly to him at the Army in <hi>Flanders. Placidia</hi> following her counſel wrote a Love-letter with reproaches to the Colonel, and found the means to have the Letter carried to the Poſt without being ſeen, for that being now Profeſſed ſhe had more liberty. This Letter came ſafe to the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel's hands, eight days before the Caſſation of the Troups, which was made upon the concluſion of the Peace. It was conceived in theſe terms.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Thoſe who love but little, do not love at all. This is your vice, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd Lover, the ambition and glory whereof you are too greedy, make you
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151646:30"/>forget what you are owing to Love: you do not love at all, becauſe you love but little. An abſence of above two years, aſſures me, that you have for me, if not contempt, at leaſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than indifference. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture from ſo prodigious a ſilence, that your heart has engaged it ſelf to another. Be not ſurprized if I call you perjur'd, for either you are ſo to me or to her, whom you are now making Oaths to of fidelity. Oblige me to change my Opinion. Have I not waited ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently? will it be ſeaſonable, for we to give my ſelf up to the ſweets of love, when with a declining age they will be become inſipid to me? Will you be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to the pleaſures of happy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, when Fatigues and military labours ſhall have as much ruined your Body as they have hardened your Heart? If you are ſtill alive, my dear Colonel, come bring me the happy news your ſelf, and if you are not bold enough to undertake the freeing me from the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151646:30"/>I am in, come at leaſt and ſet at liberty the perſon who has loved you with the moſt violent of all paſſions, and is the moſt conſtant and moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of her ſex,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Placidia.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>If ever man was ſurprized, our Colonel was ſo then when this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was delivered him. He received it as a preſent come from Heaven, he read it over and over, and it had ſuch an effect upon his Soul that he departed immediately for <hi>Paris,</hi> with a reſolution to go think then ſeriouſly of the means of bringing to paſs the enterprize of ſtealing away his Miſtreſs. The young Marquis, over whom he had got great credit, and who ſeem'd abſolutely to depend on his counſel, did not quit him. He accompanied him with his own Horſes as far as <hi>Paris,</hi> where ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151646:31"/>they lodged together. When they had repoſed there for eight days they got new Cloathes, and the Colonel pretending to go a Journey into the Countrey for three or four days, during which the Marquis, who cauſed a Coat to be embroidered, was expecting its being finiſh'd that he might go to <hi>Avenay</hi> in the equipage of a Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Spark.</p>
            <p>But the Colonel preceded him, attended onely by one Servant, a robuſt man, who had been a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier in his Regiment. Though he might have askt for the Reverend Mother <hi>Placidia</hi> at the Parlour without apprehending being denied the ſight of her, he nevertheleſs ſtill took the ancient quality of Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Pages, by which he was already known in the Abbey. <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidia</hi> had notice of his arrival, which ſurprized her to that degree, that ſhe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151646:31"/>could hardly go a ſtep. She came alone to the Grate, and expected there, almoſt without the Colonel, who had miſtaken one Parlour for another; when that having percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him to enter into that wherein ſhe was, ſhe was ſo ſeized with joy at the ſight of him, that ſhe fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a fainting fit, which deprived her of ſpeech for above half a quarter of an hour. Never was Lover in a greater perplexity than our Colonel, ſeeing that young Maid without any motion, and without any ſign of life extended after a negligent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and in the poſture her ſwoon had laid her upon a Chair. His wiſhes to give her help were all in vain, a troubleſome Grate not lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it in his power. He thought that in ſo mortifying an adventure there was no remedy but patience, not thinking it convenient to call people, for fear of giving an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to a ſuſpicion which would
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151646:32"/>have broke his meaſures. <hi>Placidia</hi> recovered from her ſwoon, gave a great ſigh, and ſaid, addreſſing her ſelf to the Colonel with a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing voice, <hi>Do you live ſtill, my dear</hi>—but was not able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed any farther, a torrent of tears for joy ſtifling her ſpeech. Her tears excited thoſe of the Colonel, and rendred him mute. They viewed one another for ſome time, their eyes doing the office of the tongue; and the Colonel at length, as being ſtronger than <hi>Placidia,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, <hi>Yes, my lovely Child, I ſtill live for you more than for my ſelf, and I am come hither to aſſure you that I am ready to expoſe a thouſand lives to free you from ſlavery. Do but ſuggeſt to me the ſureſt means for your delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Let us not loſe time in uſeleſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, I impatiently long for thoſe happy moments, and thoſe Lands ſtill unknown, whither we will make a happy retreat.</hi> To which our young Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151646:32"/>having made anſwer that ſhe conſented to all, and was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to run all manner of hazards; it was concluded between them without any farther debate, that on the <hi>Thurſday</hi> come fortnight follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, at eleven a clock in the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exactly, the Colonel ſhould come within a hundred paces of the Abbey, near the ruined of a little Houſe, which ſtood upon the ſide of a High way, that from thence he ſhould ſend his Servant with a Suit of Mens Cloaths to the Walls of the Convent Garden, that ſhe ſhould dreſs her ſelf by favour of the night, and in that diſguiſe come to him. And that they might not fail in this deſign, the Colonel had on purpoſe brought his Servant with him, who was inſtructed with what he had to doe. They both parted after ſome ſoft and melting farewells, and the Colonel made haſte to <hi>Paris</hi> for the putting of all things in order. The
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151646:33"/>Marquis having notice of his return, came to take his leave of him, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning to go viſit <hi>Placidia,</hi> whoſe Mother he had ſeen at the Play the day before. The Colonel in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe fearing the conduct of this imaginary Rival, deſired him that he would preſent his moſt humble reſpects to that Fair one, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with her the means of procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her the ſatisfaction which he did not doubt but ſhe had a long time ſighed for.</p>
            <p>Our Marquis arrived at <hi>Avenay,</hi> diſcourſed <hi>Placidia,</hi> who ſeem'd at firſt much aſtoniſhed, he made no mention of the Colonel. In that firſt interview, whether that ſhe thought the better to conceal the deſign ſhe had contrived, or that ſhe really apprehended that the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel would fail his word, ſhe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to be ſtollen away by the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis, but appointed the time three days after that projected with the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151646:33"/>Colonel. The Marquis at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn alighted from his Horſe at his ſecret Rival's Inn, gave him a deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Placidia</hi>'s new charms, and a relation of what had paſſed and was concluded between her and him. He ſpent the Afternoon with that Friend, with whom he made a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch, wherein they drank ſeveral times to the good ſucceſs of his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize.</p>
            <p>While that they amuſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves after Supper in playing at Picquet, their Servants drank libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and the Wine getting into their Noddles, they laid open their hearts to one another. The Marquis's Man Embracing his Camrade told him, <hi>Faith I am mad we muſt part ſo ſoon;</hi> to whom the other replied, <hi>and I am ſo too, perhaps for all our lives. Yet it is commonly ſaid that the mountains never meet, but of men the contrary often happens.</hi> Whereupon he asked him where his Maſter was
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151646:34"/>going? <hi>Into</hi> Italy, replied he ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: <hi>And mine ſo too,</hi> replied the Colonel's Servant, <hi>without doubt in the Company of</hi>— purſued the other who had a mind to pump him. <hi>In the company,</hi> added this indiſcreet fellow, <hi>of young Mother</hi> Placidia, <hi>whom he is to ſteal away on</hi> Thurſday <hi>come ſev'night, and for whom he had already caus'd a Man's ſuit of Apparel to be made, which I make no ſcruple to reveal to you, becauſe I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you capable of keeping it ſecret. I am ſo,</hi> continued he, <hi>and s'death I had rather be hanged than obliged to betray a ſecret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was ſufficient for the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis's Servant, who as he put his Maſter to Bed that Evening gave him the whole Hiſtory of the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel's voyage into <hi>Italy.</hi> He made him repeat it the next Morning, and enquired exactly of all the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances he had learnt of the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel's enterprize, and of the time he
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151646:34"/>was to execute it, which having learnt conformably to the truth, he forbid this fellow upon pain of being turn'd away, not to ſay a word to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny body whomſoever that he knew the intrigue, and ordered him to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from his Cronie's company. This young Cavalier converſed with the Colonel ſince that time with as much equality, though he look'd upon him in his Soul as a perfidious Rival, as if he had known nothing of his treachery. The day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed being come, the Colonel came to take his leave of him. The Marquis knew ſo well then how to command his reſentment, that he let not the leaſt ſign appear as might diſcover his fatal reſolution, but wiſht his friend a happy Journey. The Colonel departed on a Spaniſh Horſe for <hi>Rhemes,</hi> attended by his Servant, who rid on a Mare loaded with a heavy Portmantoe. The Marquis outraged at the Colonel's
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151646:35"/>perfidiouſneſs followed him at half a leagues diſtance attended by his Servant. He ſo well obſerv'd the traces of him, who went before him, that he departed from <hi>Rhemes</hi> a quarter of an hour after him. The Colonel not ſuſpecting any thing, being arrived at the place of the Rendeſvouz, ſent by his Servant the Cavalier's apparel to <hi>Placidia,</hi> who had no ſooner received it, than that ſhe gave order to the fellow to go rejoin his Maſter, and give him hopes he ſhould ſee her preſently. This Servant being oh foot, had hardly got to the Chapel, near which the Colonel his Maſter was expecting on Horſeback, when he heard two Cavaliers coming full gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop a-croſs the Field, of whom the one ſaid to the other, <hi>Here they are, here they are.</hi> He was opening his mouth to give notice to the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, when the Marquis, followed by his Man, fired a Piſtol in the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151646:35"/>Air, crying, <hi>It is thee, perfidious Rival, that I ſeek for.</hi> The Colonel ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized to hear the Marquis's voice, was putting himſelf in a poſture to Parry the inſult; when he received in his Stomach three Bullets from a Muſqueton, which that young Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier let fly at him before he had time to ward the danger. Theſe wounds fell'd him from his Horſe, and he expired in a moment after.</p>
            <p>Theſe Aſſaſſinates had time to withdraw before that the Colonel's Servant, being in a maze, did think of ſuccouring his Maſter. He ran to him, and having neither found in him breath nor ſenſe, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſembled all his ſtrength to carry him into the little Deſart Chapel, where he laid him at length. Then went he, out of his wits, to go meet <hi>Placidia,</hi> when he ſaw her coming towards him ſo nimbly as did ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſpeak the joy ſhe had at her Deliverance. She asked him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151646:36"/>all tranſported, <hi>Where is my Lover?</hi> the fellow ſtruck dumb, not being able to give her an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, took her by the hand, led her into the Chapel, to contemplate there the moſt fatal of all ſpectacles. <hi>Placidia</hi> near her Lover, whom ſhe thought aſleep, thuncht with her hand to wake him; but the inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſleeping an eternal ſleep, was without any motion. She put her hand a ſecond time upon him, as it were to tickle him, which ſhe drew back all over bloudy, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecturing any thing of what had happened, turning towards the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, ſhe asked him if he had not killed his Maſter, and if he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to make her an acceſſory to the Murther? to which the poor fellow made anſwer, <hi>No, Madam, I am not the Authour of my Maſter's death, but the Marquis, who has a long time ſigh'd for you, was not able to ſuffer a Rival in a Friend.</hi> At
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151646:36"/>theſe words, <hi>Placidia</hi> giving a ſhriek, bid him hold her up, and then fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted away in his Armes. She remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſometime in that condition, from which being recovered, ſhe caſt her ſelf upon the Body of her departed Lover, whom ſhe deified and embraced with fentiments of ſo mortal a regret, that ſhe would doubtleſs have expired upon him, if the Servant, who foreſaw whither the paſſion of this tender Maid would tend to, had he not forced her from the Corpſe, and had he not carried her with ſome violence out of the Chapel, into which he would not ſuffer her to return untill he ſaw her ſomething recollected from her firſt motions. A hundred co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations agitated <hi>Placidia</hi>'s mind in that moment. She firſt deſign'd to return into the Convent, which might have been done without ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, and a moment after changing her reſolution, ſhe turned her
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151646:37"/>thoughts towards a thouſand places whither her deſtiny might conduct her. She abandoned her ſelf at length to blind fortune, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging her ſelf againſt the tyranny of fate, ſhe returned into the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, commanded the Servant to empty his Maſter's Pockets, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken his Table-book, wrote therein by favour of the Moon theſe harſh lines which ſhe addreſſed to the Abbeſs, who was the Lady of the place.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Your ſelf-intereſted zeal has occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this Murther. You ought not in concert with an unnatural Mother have put me in Chains. If you will take a juſt revenge on me, tear out the Heart of this too faithfull Lover, and plunge therein a Poignard. It is the Heart of <hi>Placidia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:151646:37"/>
            <p>This energick Invective took up near four Pages of the Table-book. She laid them open upon the dead man's Stomach; which being done, the Servant helped her to get on Horſeback, and followed her, after ſhe had promiſed him, that to what place ſoever they went, ſhe would make his fortune. She went eight leagues afterwards without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing, after which, having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a morſel, ſhe took Horſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and continued by great days Journeys her way as far as <hi>Lyons,</hi> where ſhe refreſhed her ſelf after in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible fatigues. She cauſed there very magnificent Mourning Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel to be made for her, and put her Servant in a good equipage. As ſhe went every Evening to take the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement of the Play-houſe, ſhe could not but be taken notice of there. All people conſidered a young Cavalier ſo well made as a man of high condition. The Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151646:38"/>of <hi>Count de la Mark,</hi> which he took, fortified this belief. She li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at a high rate, which made ſome Rogues reſolve and agree to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to rob her. For that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they waited till about nine a Clock in the Evening that ſhe came from the Comedy, and attackt her upon a little Bridge. Her Servant ſtood ſtoutly to it, while that <hi>Placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> whom we will henceforward call the <hi>Count de la Mark,</hi> or plainly the young Count, made her eſcape. This faithfull Servant reſiſted theſe Robbers the beſt he was able, untill at length being ſurrounded by them, he was thrown by thoſe Rogues from off the Bridge into the River where he was drowned.</p>
            <p>Our young Count loſt a great deal in this Servant; he ſeem'd for ſome days extremely grieved for his misfortune, and inferred from all theſe accidents that he was the mark of deſtiny, againſt which he
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151646:38"/>took a reſolution to ſtruggle. He took a <hi>Valet de Chambre</hi> who knew nothing of all his affairs, whom he carried with him to the Court of <hi>Savoy,</hi> whither he went immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after his arrival at <hi>Turin</hi> to pay his reſpects to her Royal Highneſs. That Auguſt Princeſs, charmed with the happy Phyſiognomy of this young Count, took an affection for him, and ordered him not to quit the Court. He became very aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duous there, appearing after a very gallant manner, which mov'd Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Royal to give him teſtimonies of her benign inclination. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he had not been at Court above two months when ſhe gratified him with a Company of Foot; the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders being that the Officers ſhould not abandon the Garriſon: the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment wherein the <hi>Count de la Mark</hi> had a Company being at <hi>Verceil,</hi> when that he wrent to take leave of her Highneſs, ſhe gave him leave
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151646:39"/>to return to Court after 3 months reſidence. He employed that time in taking tinctures of all the exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes becoming his Profeſſion, both of Riding and Fencing. The three months being expired, he returned to Court, where having paſſed ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral months without that any Beauty being able to triumph over his indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, Madam Royal told him one day ſmiling: <hi>But,</hi> Count de la Mark, <hi>how long will you continue in an indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference injurious to the fair Ladies? How, will you be all mays inſenſible? or rather is this Court ſo barren in objects worthy any paſſion, that there is not one capable of ſtaggering your reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</hi> This obliging way of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from ſo Illuſtrious a Princeſs ſeem'd to him to merit a juſt anſwer, and as he had an infinite deal of wit, he told Madam Royal: <hi>Madam, the Graces make their reſidence in this Court, and if I have ſo long deferred to ſacrifice to ſome one of thoſe Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151646:39"/>the reaſon is, becauſe I cannot without rendring my ſelf culpable of an injurious preference determine my ſelf to any one in particular, the moſt part of the Ladies, who have the honour to approach your Royal Highneſs, having all I know not what that's ſingular to my eyes; Inſomuch, Madam, that I am all ready to love, and ſhould not think my ſelf deceived in my choice, if I had the advantage of receiving an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination from the hands of your Royal Highneſs. This Diſpoſition,</hi> reaſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Madam Royal, <hi>is rather an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition to love, than the mark of a real paſſion. People ought onely to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, in the choice of an object, the motions of a natural inclination: ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy is the mother of Love, and it is onely from it that it can take its riſe. Nevertheleſs, if you can conceive a Love more than one of complaiſance for her I might propoſe to you, love</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle Berenice, <hi>ſhewing her to him, but love her ſincerely, if it be
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151646:40"/>poſſible, and you will without doubt find how highly ſhe does merit it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the ſex of our young Count did not cauſe any greater emotion in him in the preſence of the one than of the other, he would needs ſhew by dwelling upon this election the eſteem he had of her Royal Highneſs's choice. He turned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the beautifull <hi>Berenice,</hi> and made her a declaration of Love, with ſo much wit that all the Court was ſurprized and charmed with its juſtneſs. And indeed he laid to her a great many pretty things, and conjured her, through the reſpect he had for Madam Royal, that ſhe would accept of his Compliments for the future. This young Lady, who had been born and bred at Court, and was no leſs witty than handſome, repartie'd very ingeniouſly to the young Count, whom ſhe already lov'd by inclination, and told him very gallantly that he ought not to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151646:40"/>amuſe her to no purpoſe, but to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to what her heart ſhould ſay to him of her, and to give her a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full account of it. Thus the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation ended, this new Miſtreſs following Madam Royal, who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew into her Cabinet.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Count de la Mark</hi> being thus engaged, when he leaſt thought of courting a Miſtreſs, imagining that an amorous commerce which ſhould take its riſe from an unforeſeen oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion would onely follow an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary train, and would not ſo ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be terminated, returned the ſame evening to Court, where he had onely eyes for <hi>Berenice,</hi> and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able replies for the propoſitions of that facetious Miſtreſs. He told her that very moment ſo many nice and pleaſant things, that being char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with his wit, ſhe immediately grew familiar with him, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him afterwards ſomething more reſerved. This illuſtrious Traveſty
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151646:41"/>thinking himſelf obliged to live at ſomething a higher rate, becauſe ſince the honour he had received from Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Royal he was reſpected by all people, he quitted his Inn to go take a Lodging in the principal place of the Town, and where commonly all ſtrangers of Quality lodge who travel to <hi>Turin.</hi> Sitting down one day to Table at an Ordinary, he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Marquis, the Colonel her Lover's Murtherer, who ſeated himſelf oppoſite to her. He was arrived ſome days before at <hi>Turin</hi> from <hi>Germany,</hi> whither he retired after the aſſaſſination of his Rival. He had there heard ſo advantageous an account of the Count's Qualities, that he had a ſtrong inclination to be of his acquaintance, and this was what had invited him thither. Our young Count knew him immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, but the Marquis had not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved any <hi>Idea</hi> of him, inſomuch that during Dinner the diſcourſe was
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151646:41"/>wholly upon indifferent things. The Marquis having obſerved by the Count's converſation, that the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of his wit was anſwerable to the pourtraict all the Court made of it, courted his familiarity, and engaged with him in a commerce of Friendſhip which outwardly ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med very intimate. The Count nevertheleſs kept in the bottom of his heart ſentiments of revenge which ſuddenly broke forth by the death of that ambitious Rival, for ſee what followed afterwards.</p>
            <p>Since the Marquis was arrived at Court, his young heart not being able to remain in repoſe, he made viſits to the lovely perſon, for whom the Count ſeemed to ſigh. He fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied himſelf very far in her eſteem, though <hi>Berenice</hi> had no inclinations but for our illuſtrious Traveſty. He knew the Count viſited her, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver having met him at her apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he thought himſelf onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151646:42"/>and it was this ridiculous o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion that coſt him his life. The young Count, who onely made his vows to <hi>Berenice</hi> at Court, not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming that ſentiments declared in publick would be taken for ſincere, upon her reproaching him one day that he told all the world except her ſelf that he was in love with her, becauſe he never went to give her aſſurances of it at her Chamber, he went on the morrow morning and found her in Bed. There it was that he found himſelf obliged to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain her with ſoft and amarous Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, which had ſo ſenſible an effect upon <hi>Berenice,</hi> that ſhe told him gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantly after an hours familiar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, <hi>Count, the reſt to morrow.</hi> Though this manner of aſſignation ſeem'd to him ſomething too liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, he did believe that at Court, where affairs are a long time before they come to conſummation, in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Love they were terminated <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:151646:42"/>expedited ſo ſoon. He returned on the morrow at the ſame hour, with a deſign to take his leave of <hi>Bere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> for a month, which he ſaid he was to employ in reforming ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes in his Company, flattered with the hopes this ſpace of time might ſtifle the flames of that young Maid. But he was too tardy, and will have another ſort of Journey to take. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renice,</hi> who had impatiently expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him in her Bed, had garniſhed her head with Cornets of point of <hi>Venice,</hi> with gawdy Ribbons, mixt with <hi>Griſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delin,</hi> white and blue, whoſe colours were as many ſymbols: ſhe had, in ſhort, decked her ſelf with all the ornaments that could render her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable in the ſtate ſhe was. The Count ſeeing her in that poſture did make but ill conjecture of the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of his viſit, made her a very Gentleman-like Compliment, and told her though the company of two Officers would have engaged him
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151646:43"/>to take Horſe that morning for <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeil,</hi> he was nevertheleſs unwilling to depart without coming to pay her his civilities; that his friends wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for him with all imaginable im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience, and that he deſired her to give him leave to obey the Orders of her Highneſs. <hi>Berenice</hi> at any others time would have contented her ſelf with a Compliment, but the amorous paſſion which ruled her put into her mouth ſuch engaging words, that our Count cruelly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plext could not civilly diſpence from entertaining her for a moment. He approach'd her Bed-ſide, near which having found no Chair, becauſe ſhe had cauſed them all to be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way on purpoſe, ſhe prevented him, and gave him the liberty to ſit upon her Bed. If ever Lover was in a conſternation it was the Count, who ſeem'd at that moment without ſpeech, motion or ſenſe. <hi>Berenice</hi> perceiving the diſtraction
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151646:43"/>he was under, ask'd him what ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him ſo penſive? to which this Lover againſt his will made her no other anſwer than by a ſmile, which gave her occaſion to believe that he was burnt with the ſame amorous deſire as her ſelf. When ſhe ſaw him ſeated by her, her fire mounted into her face, ſhe ask'd the Count with a confidence which was but little allayed by modeſty: <hi>Is it true, Count, that you love me? you have ſworn you do a thouſand times, but the faith of a Cavalier, having always been ſuſpected by me, you may now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſome your ſelf to me, and make me know if the force of your love is anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the vehemence of mine.</hi> The Count put to his trumps by theſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, ready to obtain what any other would have called the higheſt favour, pretended he would make her a very ſoft and amorous anſwer. He ſaid, <hi>Why has not Heaven, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>— when that he got up haſtily
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151646:44"/>and went towards the Door, as if it were to ſurprize ſome body who had the curioſity to liſten to their diſcourſe. He proceeded on as far as the Stair-caſe, from whence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing returned, pretending anger to <hi>Berenice,</hi> he cried, <hi>My God, Madam, your Servants are very curious, I hate ſuch people like the Peſt.</hi> Whether that <hi>Berenice</hi> gueſſed he had really heard ſome body, or that ſhe was ſcandalized at his freedom, ſhe ſeem'd netled to the quick at this diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Count's, whom from that time ſhe treated with, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt neglect and ſcorn. From that very moment ſhe took an averſion to him, and told him with a tone as did ſufficiently ſpeak her vexation, <hi>Without doubt, my Lord, the thoughts of your being expected, took from you all other application, and you fancied by preoccupation the arrival of ſome body: beſides, we ſaid nothing but what might have been heard without
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151646:44"/>ſcandal by all the world, at leaſt unleſs you were upon the point of beginning ſome ſilly idle diſcourſe.</hi> The <hi>Count de la Mark</hi> who was offended at the words, yet did ſeem to take notice of the reaſons which animated her to uſe them, to him. He ask'd her pardon for die fault he had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and took his leave, of her, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving her in an alteration capable of framing deſigns of the moſt cruel revenge.</p>
            <p>As ſhe was deliberating in her ſelf about the means of drawing ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for a contempt which paſs'd in her mind for the moſt ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of all outrages, the Marquis, who ſeldom fail'd to ſee her at her dreſſing, entred her Chamber, where he remain'd ſome time without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to get a word from her. It was to no purpoſe for him to inquire of the ſtate of her health, and of the occaſion which obliged her to ſigh. She made him no anſwer but by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubling
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151646:45"/>of ſobs, which caſt him into the like conſternation. After having acted a long time the part of a Woman, whom exceſs of grief had deprived of her ſenſes, having ſhed tears that had as it were reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her to her uſual ſerenity, ſhe her ſelf reanimated her diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ask'd the Marquis with ſuch an accent of voice as was the interpreter of her deſpair, if he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her ſincerely enough to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace her intereſts, and help her to ſtab a Ponyard in the breaſt of the moſt criminal of all men. <hi>Yes, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> replied the Marquis; <hi>thoſe who vex-you, or have the diſadvantage of diſpleaſing you, offend me mortally, and there is nothing but what I would undertake and hazard for the drawing a juſt ſatisfaction. Who is this perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious perſon you complain of? tell me onely his name, without declaring to me his crime; he is culpable ſince you judge him ſo, and he muſt either take
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151646:45"/>away my life, with the tranquillity which he has raviſhed from you, or waſh in his bloud the crime he has committed.</hi> The diſpoſition wherein <hi>Berenice</hi> ſaw the Marquis to revenge the inſult which ſhe ſaid had been done her, did ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently flatter her reſentment ſo as to give him liberty to continue ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>That young</hi> Count de la Mark, added ſhe, <hi>whoſe inſipid Courtſhip I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard but at Court, being flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a vain hopes, that one of my ways of ſaying things after a gallant manner did yeſterday inſpire him with, came early this morning to make me a viſit, entred my Chamber, ſaluted me, ſate familiarly upon my Bed, and after having entertained me romantickly of the flames which devoured his heart, approached his head to my Pillow, and by ſurprize kiſſed me, and his hands would have taken other liberty if I had not vigorouſly repulſed them, and if the ſhriek which I gave had not made him deſiſt from his inſolent enterprize.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151646:46"/>See,</hi> purſued that malicious Maid, <hi>what has put me in the trouble you ſee me under; judge, my dear Marquis, if I am without reaſon in a rage, and if it is not with juſtice, that I demand ſatisfaction for ſo criminal a freedom.</hi> The Marquis, giving credit to the words and tears of <hi>Berenice,</hi> took vigorouſly her part, declared againſt the Count's temerity and inſolence, which he judged worthy of being checked, and which he offered to puniſh immediately. <hi>Berenice</hi> after having made him promiſes capable of making him venture at all, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the intereſt of her offended honour into his hands and manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, conjuring him not to defer taking a juſt ſatisfaction. This was ſufficient to inflame the already boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling bloud of the Marquis, he left <hi>Berenice</hi> without ſaying to her a word more, and flew to the Count's Lodging, who was at Breakfaſt with one of his Friends. He invited him
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151646:46"/>to partake with them; they drank ſome glaſſes of Wine together, and then having taken the Count aſide, he told him nevertheleſs aloud e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: <hi>You know, my Lord, what has paſſed between</hi> Mademoiſelle Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renice <hi>and you; if you are as couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as you are paſſionate you will meet me with your Friend, who ſhall ſerve for a witneſs of the action, in the Wood behind the White Houſe, about eleven a clock, and there we will end the quarrel in which I am concerned.</hi> The <hi>Count de la Mark,</hi> having a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times ſought an occaſion to quarrel with the Marquis, in whom that beautifull Traveſty had never been able to reſolve to pardon the murther of her Lover, did joyfully accept the Challenge, gave him his hand, invited him to doe the ſame, after which the Marquis withdrew. The Cavalier who had been preſent at the Challenge, inſtead of endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring a reconciliation, did ſtill
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151646:47"/>animate the Count the more, and very luckily lent him a pair of Buff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skin Gloves. The Marquis had waited ſome time for the <hi>Count de la Mark,</hi> when he very luckily came to the Rendeſvouz. Theſe two il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Combatants embraced one another, and immediately took Sword in hand. This laſt having learnt but three months, and having not ſo ſtrong a hand as his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, did not ſtand very ſtiff to it at firſt, which made the Cavalier believe, who was preſent at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, that they were not equally matcht, and made him reſolve to ſtrike down their Swords to part them, when that of the Marquis pointed unluckily into the Buff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glove, wherewith the Count's left hand was armed and left this laſt time to run him in a mortal wound which rendred the Marquis uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of purſuing the fight. The <hi>Count de la Mark</hi> having thus gained
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151646:47"/>the Victory, bid the wounded man ask his life. The Marquis begg'd it accordingly, but it was too late, he fell down upon the ground, and loſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly his life with his bloud, when our young Conquerour told this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy dying man. <hi>I would I could reſtore it thee, though thou doſt not deſerve it. But ſince thy ill deſtiny does rather deprive thee of it than my dexterity, know it is with delight that I deprive thee of it, and that it is from Heaven that my Arm receives the force of revenging my Lover to day. If thy agony leaves thee ſtill any ſenſe and knowledge, open thy eyes, look and know</hi> Placidia <hi>under the juſt inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which proves thy fall, and go tell my dear Colonel, whoſe baſe and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable aſſaſſinate thou wert, that I love him ſtill, and that he is revenged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the name of <hi>Placidia</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis opened his eyes again; he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collected all the ſtrength he had left in that extremity and told this
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151646:48"/>young Conquerour: <hi>Are you</hi> Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidia? and exhaled with theſe words his laſt gaſp. The laſt ſervice which our young Count could render to this unfortunate Cavalier was to lend him his Arm to draw him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing farther into the Wood, where he covered his Body with Leaves. After an accident of this nature he did not think it ſafe for him to tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry any longer at <hi>Turin.</hi> He went in all haſte to the City, where he went to declare what was done to Madam Royal, into whoſe hands he remitted his life. That generous Princeſs, who honoured him with her good will, ordered him to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from Court, and for a mark of her clemency caus'd Letters to be diſpatched in favour of him to her Reſident at the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> What inclination ſoever he had to ſee that Court, he had the curioſity to know the City of <hi>Genoa,</hi> and to make ſome abode there for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151646:48"/>Whereupon he ſet forwards for that Town, after having enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the perſon by Oath, who had been preſent at the Duel, and a witneſs of his Victory, not to engage his ſearch. And then he changed his Quality of <hi>Count de la Mark</hi> into that of <hi>Chevalier de Saleuze,</hi> and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at <hi>Genoa.</hi> The deſtiny to which he had abandoned himſelf en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely, furniſhed him with an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of making acquaintance with one of the principal inhabitants of the City whither he was going, whoſe wit and humour were of a man of his Quality, and not of his Age of ſeventy years. In ſpeaking of ſeveral things, that venerable old man finding that this young Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, with whoſe converſation he was charmed, deſigned to make ſome ſtay at <hi>Genoa</hi> for his diverſion, and knowing the Town, he offered him his Houſe, and engaged to board him for three months. Our <hi>Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:151646:49"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:151646:49"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:151646:50"/>having found that he was no ſelf-intereſted man, accepted his offer and alighted at his Houſe, where he found none but reſpectfull domeſticks cloathed in mourning, by reaſon their Maſter had been a Widower about ſix months. He had two Chambers appointed him in the fineſt Apartment over thoſe of the Daughter of the family, whom her Father had newly carried to <hi>Turin</hi> to ſpend ſome time with a Lady a friend of hers. The <hi>Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier de Saleuze</hi> did not abuſe the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity of his Hoſt, but treated him always with the higheſt reſpect. Theſe regards did extremely pleaſe the Magiſtrate, who judged by the Gentile and civil carriage of his Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionary that he was a perſon of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable extraction. He took an affection for him, and without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining to the bottom who he was he fancied he ſhould not be diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by his alliance. As they one
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151646:50"/>day came back from walking and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the Houſe, <hi>Mademoiſelle Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtica</hi> being newly returned from <hi>Turin</hi> came to embrace her Father, who commanded her to preſent her Cheek to the young <hi>Chevalier.</hi> She executed this order with a very good grace, and afterwards gave an account to her Father of what ſhe had done ſince their ſeparation. Supper was in the mean while pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, which being ſerved upon the Table, and the <hi>Chevalier</hi> thinking he was obliged to ſhew ſomething more than indifference, took a ſeat very near that of <hi>Mademoiſelle Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtica,</hi> who was a Maid of a ſingular beauty, and though ſhe had hardly attained the ſixteenth year of her age, was likewiſe very ingenious and witty. Amongſt other things which ſhe ſaid to have heard at Court, ſhe ſaid that a Cavalier had flattered her with being capable of inſpiring, and receiving the impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:151646:51"/>of Love. Her Father attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this freedom of ſpeaking her ſentiments to her innocence, enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of her the name of the perſon from whom ſhe had received this Compliment. <hi>From a young Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier of this Gentleman's age,</hi> replied ſhe, ſhewing the Chevalier, <hi>who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded too that he wiſh'd he could be ſo happy as to make me in love. Schola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtica</hi>'s Governeſs, who knew the Cavalier, ſpoke his name aloud, who being very well known by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he ſaid that that young Spark was accuſtomed to make Court to all young Women, and that credit was not to be given to all gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. This old man took delight in obſerving the eyes of his Penſionary, who held them almoſt always ſixt upon <hi>Scholaſtica,</hi> to whom he thought it was his devoir ſo to doe out of policy. After ſome diſcourſes which ſufficiently ſhew'd the character of his Daughter's ſimplicity, he askt
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151646:51"/>the Chevalier, <hi>Well, Sir, what do you think of this innocent Creature? Is ſhe worthy to be look'd upon by a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier?</hi> Whereupon our young Spark replied, <hi>That</hi> Mademoiſelle Schola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtica <hi>was ſovereignly amiable, and that there were Princes who ſhould eſteem themſelves perfectly happy to be in her favour.</hi> This anſwer flattered the weak ſide that this old man had for his Daughter, and put the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier more into his mind than ever. During three months that our Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier ſpent in <hi>Scholaſtica</hi>'s familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and company, as a Brother with a Siſter, the old man having obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved nothing in the conduct that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited the leaſt reproach, he concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for him ſo extraordinary an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, that without knowing him otherwiſe he deſigned him his Daughter. As he was very glad ſhe ſhould be beloved, he took him one day aſide, and ſounded his diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as to her. This illuſtrious Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſty
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151646:52"/>who could have wiſh'd to have been capable of ſo fine an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? did modeſtly declare to <hi>Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtica</hi>'s Father that he had always e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed <hi>Mademoiſelle</hi> his Daughter worthy of being courted, and that if he had never appeared paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate for her, the reaſon was not that her charms had left his heart in repoſe, but becauſe he knew the inviolable fidelity which was due to hoſpitality. So wiſe and prudent an anſwer charm'd the old man, who told the Chevalier, that if he had any inclination for his Daughter, he might freely declare to him his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents, and that he would prepare her to liſten to him favourably. Our Chevalier ſince this notice had all the complaiſances imaginable for <hi>Mademoiſelle Scholaſtica,</hi> to whom he acquitted himſelf of all the devoirs of a real Lover.</p>
            <p>The Carnaval time being very near, the old man, who was of a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151646:52"/>ſtrong complexion, that had not yet loft the reliſh worldly pleaſures, being accuſtomed to go every year to <hi>Venice</hi> to take his ſhare there in the publick Divertiſements that are juſt before Lent, propoſed the jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to his Boarder whom he found diſpoſed to all he had a mind.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the general debauches our Chevalier knew how to keep a temperament between diſſolution and too much reſervedneſs, and his conduct ſeem'd in all things to the old man ſo full of wiſedom, that he jud'gd he could not find a more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Husband to his Daughter. As he was lookt favourably upon by the Great Duke, going one day to pay him his devoirs, that Prince askt him what was become of his Daughter, and if ſhe was married? to which the old man repertie'd, that he was upon the point of giving her in marriage to a foreign Gentleman, in whom he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ſuch fine qualities, that he gueſs'd <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:151646:53"/>at the greatneſs of his extraction by the purity of his manners. The Prince teſtified that he ſhould be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry glad to ſee him, which mov'd the old man to engage him to come kiſs his moſt ſerene Highneſ's hands, which he had the honour to doe, and the Grand Duke ſeem'd very well ſatisfied with him, and told the Magiſtrate in his preſence that he did not believe he would be deceived in his choice, that he would be at the charge of the Wedding, and would honour them with his preſence. Such obliging offers from ſo great a Prince did quite deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the reſolution of <hi>Scholaſtica</hi>'s Father, who promiſed her in the Grand Duke's Chamber to our Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, who found himſelf too much honoured with ſo tickliſh a prefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence as not to give his conſent to a Match ſo glorious for him, which was projected for a certain day. As ſoon as our old man was returned
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151646:53"/>to his home, he call'd for his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and as he was the abſolute Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of her will, he commanded her to give her hand and faith to our Chevalier. <hi>Scholaſtica</hi> obeyed her Father's orders with great ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and likewiſe embraced very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morouſly the Chevalier, who for his part vow'd to her an eternal fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: the Nuptial Ceremonies were prepared without much hurry, and all was made ready by orders from the Great Duke in one of his moſt ſtately Houſes of pleaſure for the day of Marriage.</p>
            <p>Deſtiny conducted things to ſuch a term as gave a great deal of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet to our illuſtrious Traveſty. He ſufficiently ſought the occaſion to ſteal away during the hurry of the Ceremonies, but ſome or other of the Company never leaving him hindred him for putting his deſigns in execution, inſomuch that it came to the Solemnities of the Marriage,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151646:54"/>which were celebrated in the Chapel of the Caſtle, with all the pomp ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable. Our Chevalier reſolved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt fate, had not the time to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute with himſelf, and ſaw himſelf conſtrained to paſs from the Church to the Banquets prepared in Services of the Prince's gilt Vermillion. He lent his good humour to the Feaſt, which the Grand Duke honoured with his preſence, and at the Deſert drank to the happineſs of the Bride and Bridegroom. The Afternoon was ſpent in converſations, in ſports and walks, which were followed by a ſplendid Supper, and worthy of the Prince's magnificence. The Ball came afterwards, at which all the Court was preſent, and wherein all the young Lords diſputed who ſhould preſent the hand to the young Bride. Though that our uneaſie Husband foreſaw that the Company would Dance till the morrow morning, he judged he had waited but too long,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151646:54"/>and that it was time to make his Eſcape. Thus he vaniſht inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly from the Hall under pretext of ſome neceſſity, took his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant at the Door, and ſo went out of the Caſtle without having been diſtinguiſhed by the Centinel, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt a crowd of perſons, who went in and out there every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He having informed his Servant of his deſign, he had caus'd Horſes to be ready hard by, which they mounted, after having chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Clothes in the very place where they were expected. They travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all the Night, during which the Aſſembly of the invited, and the Prince inquired for him, and had him ſought for every where. It not being poſſible to find him, all the Company thought that he might have found himſelf indiſpoſed through ſome exceſs, which might have obliged him to withdraw into
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:151646:55"/>ſome private place. His abſence was the cauſe that they put an end to their mirth much earlier, and filled the Father and Daughter with cruel thoughts. They were in hopes to ſee him again at leaſt on the morrow, but their hopes were deceived, for they met with no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy who could give the leaſt tidings of him. In the mean while they were forced to digeſt their vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. All the Town went to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the old man for this mortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing adventure, at which <hi>Scholaſtica</hi> was ſo concerned, that ſhe ask'd and obtain'd from her Father the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of going to deplore in a Cloiſter ſo ſurprizing a Widowhood. True it is, that ſhe did not firſt put on the Nuns attire, and that ſhe ſtill expected very impatiently her Husband's return.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:151646:55"/>
            <p>Our <hi>Chevalier de Saleuze</hi> in the mean while arrived at <hi>Rome,</hi> where he called himſelf plainly <hi>Monſieur de la Motte.</hi> He clothed himſelf there very modeſtly, and went to pay a Viſit to the Reſident of <hi>Savoy,</hi> to whom he preſented the Letters that Madam Royal written in his favour, who in conſideration of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs made him all manner of good reception, and offered him his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. He enquired after his deſigns, if he was reſolved to ſtay in that Court, and what figure he intended to make there. The <hi>Sieur de la Motte</hi> having made him anſwer, that he was not in a condition to be at any expence, the Reſident told him, that if he had a mind to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt on ſome Benefice it lay in his power to procure him one of ſome ſmall conſequence, untill that an occaſion of ſome more conſiderable one was offered. Our illuſtrious
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151646:56"/>Traveſty liſtened to this proportion, and thought that he ought to afford himſelf likewiſe this ſort of fortune, told him that he was ſhaved, and that he ſhould have the higheſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to him if he would employ his credit to provide him the place of a Canon. About a week after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards there fell one vacant. The Reſident had notice of it, requeſted it of his Holineſs, who gratified the <hi>Sieur de la Motte</hi> with it, whom he recommended very particularly to his Biſhops. Whereupon he went to take poſſeſſion of his new Dignity, in a City twenty miles diſtance from <hi>Rome,</hi> called <hi>Ceſano,</hi> where he arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at the time of a very famous Fair, which was kept every year in that place, and which invited thither almoſt all <hi>Italy.</hi> Then he went to the Cathedral, and aſſiſted at Divine Service, which he recited with the reſt; when by the treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:151646:56"/>of his ill Deſtiny which had brought <hi>Scholaſtica</hi>'s Father thither, he was known by him. The truth is, that this old man looked upon him a long time before he could be perſuaded that it was he, and it was his bluſhing that did moſt betray him. All aided to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of his Father-in-law; for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving inquired if he had been long a Canon, he learnt that he had been ſo but one day, and that he had been received by the Chapter upon the ſolicitation of the Reſident of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy.</hi> No longer doubting but that it was he, he enquired after his Lodging, from whence he caus'd him to be taken by virtue of a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, which he had obtained againſt him. The credit of the Reſident his Protectour obtained his removal to <hi>Rome,</hi> where being put again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Priſon, two hours afterwards our old man in the higheſt rage againſt
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:151646:57"/>him went to render him a Viſit. At firſt he fell into invectives againſt him, called him Cheat and Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and ſwore he would make him ſuffer for the affront with which he had tarniſhed the honour of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. Our Canon let him ſay all that paſſion ſuggeſted to him, and after having ſeen him return'd into the ſtate of his uſual tranquillity he diſcours'd him in this manner. <hi>I do not doubt. Sir, but that you have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to complain of me, for having expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you to the becoming the May-game of the Countrey, and for having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the alliance of the Perſon in the world who ſeem'd the moſt to merit my affection: But when I ſhall have acquainted you with the Reaſons which mov'd me to ſo precipitated a Retreat, I believe you too reaſonable, not to, I will not ſay applaud, but at leaſt, not to ſomething moderate your reſentment. I had a paſſionate love,</hi> purſued he,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:151646:57"/>
               <hi>for</hi> Mademoiſelle, <hi>your Daughter, and I thought her ſenſible to my paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, flattered my ſelf that I ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone enjoy the ſweets of her Embraces; and nevertheleſs my ears have acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me that I was not the onely Object of her Vows, and that ſhe had a much greater inclination for another. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the midſt of the Ball, having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that</hi> Mademoiſelle Scholaſtica <hi>entertained familiarly a young Lord, near whom ſhe took a Seat: after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving danced, I had the Curioſity to hear what might be the ſubject of ſo familiar a Diſcourſe. I ſlipt, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie my ſelf upon that point, behind the Hangings, and thoſe two Lovers ſpoke very ſoftly: I nevertheleſs heard diſtinctly that they ſaid to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an hundred amorous things. I could wiſh, for your repoſe, for her honour, and the half of my bloud I had been deaf in that occaſion, or that the Vapours of Wine and Meats had
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151646:58"/>not given them ſuch a longing to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain one another ſo privately. But what is there more indiſcreet than a violent love! This young Lord ſaid to</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle Scholaſtica, <hi>That happy time is at length come, that we ſhall enjoy thoſe pleaſures which the eſtate of Maiden forbid us the uſe of. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven does at preſent favour our mutual flàmes, and it will onely depend on that we may live in the fineſt intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence imaginable. To which</hi> Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle, <hi>your Daughter, made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: That he ought to be perſuaded that ſhe was wholly his; that how great a horrour ſoever ſhe might always have had to marriage, ſhe had onely conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to it, that it might ſerve for a cloak to their amorous Commerce, and that they needed onely to ſeek ſure means to entertain it.</hi> The <hi>Sieur de la Motte</hi> could not make this recital without ſhedding tears, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed melted the old man, but did
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151646:58"/>not render him entirely ſatisfied. They were at:this paſs when the Reſident, Protectour of <hi>Monſieur de la Motte</hi> arrived, who was fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the things, and created Arbitratour of the Diſpute. This wiſe Mediatour ſeeing that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non confeſſed the deſertion he was accuſed of, did at firſt make him ſome remonſtrances, and told him afterwards that he muſt abſolutely reſolve to return to <hi>Genoa,</hi> to live there in a perfect concord with his dear Wife, and upon his obſerving that he had an extreme repugnance to conſent to this offer, he told the Father-in-law that he thought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for the ſatisfaction of both Parties, that he ſhould make a Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement upon his Daughter, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low her to accompany her Husband into ſome other Town or City, where, not being known, they might live in a happy Union. The
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:151646:59"/>old man ſubſcribed to the propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, conſented to the ſetting free of his Son-in-law, whom the Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent engaged to re-deliver him when that things were in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Whereupon he departed for <hi>Genoa,</hi> and our Canon went to lodge at the Reſident's Houſe, who had commanded ſecretly to one of his Domeſticks, to have always an eye upon him. The <hi>Sieur de la Motte</hi> counterfeited for ſome time, and ſeem'd to have no other deſign than of expecting with patience the arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of his Father-in-law, though he meditated his retraction to <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The old man at his return to <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa</hi> went to ſee his Daughter, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed her for the ſpace of two hours, and put her an hundred times out of countenance, and made her a hundred reproaches, which had like to have put that innocent
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:151646:59"/>Creature into deſpair, though her Tears and her Candour, which was known to him, and her Oaths did perſuade him of the contrary of what he had learnt of her: He made her reſolve nevertheleſs to comply with the deſign of her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, who intended to go paſs with her at <hi>Venice</hi> the reſt of his life; of whoſe return he was aſſured, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he powerfully flatter'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the hopes of it. Thus ſhe expected, without letting any thing be known of her deſign to the Nuns and her Companions, the time of her change of State; But ſhe learnt with a redoublement of grief that propoſition accepted by the Chevalier her Husband had onely been a ſlur by which her Father had ſuffered himſelf to be ſurprized, which made her demand the habit of a Nun, which was not refuſed, though that the year of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:151646:60"/>the Noviciates being revolved, they would not receive her vows. And indeed the Old man having ſetled his affairs, by Letters informed the Reſident of their diſpoſition, who was upon the point of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating it with the <hi>Sieur de la Motte,</hi> when word was brought him that he had made his eſcape in the morning without any bodies know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what was become of him.</p>
            <p>He had abandoned <hi>Rome</hi> and the Quality of <hi>Sieur de la Motte,</hi> to take upon him that of <hi>Chevalier,</hi> and went in all haſte to <hi>Civita Vecchia,</hi> when he embarked in a little Veſſel which he found there ready to make ſail for <hi>Lisbon.</hi> And indeed as ſoon as he was got on board, they weighed Anchor; and when that he ſaw himſelf at ſome diſtance from the Port, and free from all fears, he began to breathe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and accoſt a Portugueſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151646:60"/>called <hi>Don Alphonſo,</hi> who took a ſingular pleaſure in his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation: they ſail'd with ſo fair a Wind, that they were not long at Sea, and deſcended at the Port of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> where <hi>Don Alphonſo</hi> invited our young Traveller to take up his Quarters at his Houſe, untill that he was ſomething acquainted with the Town. He accepted the offer of that officious Portugal, ſtaid ſome days at <hi>Lisbon,</hi> and went in his Company to pay his moſt humble reſpects to the Queen, whom he had the honour to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint with the favours he had received from <hi>Madam Royal.</hi> Her Majeſty took an affection for him from that very moment, aſſured him of her Protection, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended him to <hi>Don Alphonſo,</hi> whoſe Father had the office of her Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of the Horſe. The Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of this Nobleman dwelt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151646:61"/>four Leagues from the Town, and conſiſted in a Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lady, Mother of two Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, extremely beautifull, of eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen and ſeventeen years of age, and of a Child of eight, Brother of <hi>Don Alphonſo.</hi> This obliging family neglected nothing of all that might ſerve to the Diverſion of our Chevalier, who divided his time between good Chear, Walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Hunting and Fiſhing. Though he had not in the bottom of his Soul any greater inclination for the one, than for the other, of thoſe two lovely Ladies: He obſerved ſo much ſweetneſs and conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the humour of the youngeſt with him, that he conceived for her a Love of Sympathy, which he made paſs with her for a real paſſion. The eldeſt, whoſe Mother could have wiſh'd to have been firſt provided<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with a Husband,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151646:61"/>though the youngeſt was her Darling, ſaw with a ſingular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, that our Chevalier had an Eſteem for her: This eldeſt, I ſay, became jealous of their familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to that degree, of not allowing them the leaſt conveniency of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to confer together. Her young Siſter, who was not very much in Love, but took a pride in being belov'd, perceiving that ſhe bore her a grudge for the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection that the Chevalier teſtified for her, Counſelled her pretended Favourite to diſguiſe his Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to make Love to her Siſter; and told him that ſhe ſhould take for her ſelf all that he ſhould ſay to her Siſter that was touching and tender, and that thus they might divert themſelves agreeably upon her jealouſie. The Chevalier conſented to her requeſt. But this young Lady was ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151646:62"/>as to Confide this Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Cheat in her Chamber-Maid, who went and told it immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly again to the eldeſt Siſter; who conceived ſo furious a reſentment upon it, that ſhe reſolved not to preſcribe bounds to her revenge, but to aſſaſſinate him in his way to <hi>Lisbon,</hi> whither he was to go on the morrow to <hi>Don Alphonſo,</hi> whom ſome affairs had called thither ſome days before. She gave for this execution a Ring of value, and Money, to a Peaſant, formerly a Soldier, and always of a cruel and barbarous temper, who was to have lain in Ambuſcade, and ſo have ſhot him dead. The Chevalier de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted about five a Clock in the morning, in the cool, for <hi>Lisbon,</hi> and was met upon the way by the hired aſſaſſinate. This ruſty fellow being on foot, let him paſs by, and then fired a Piſtol very near
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151646:62"/>him behind, but miſſed him. Our Chevalier being ſtartled at the noiſe, turned towards the Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, who had but one Bullet more to fire, and him he threatned to kill if he charged again, and left him not, untill by the help of ſome Paſſengers he had ſeized on him, and made ſure of his perſon. When he ſaw him in his power, he que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned him, and learnt that the eldeſt Siſter of <hi>Don Alphonſo</hi> had moved him to commit this Crime. He was not willing to put this Mercenary Criminal into the hands of Juſtice, nor to ſacrifice him to a juſt reſentment; he contented himſelf with giving him good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances without bitterneſs, and encharged him with a Letter for her, who would have ſacrificed him to the paſſion of a deteſtable jealouſie. Now this Letter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained onely theſe lines.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:151646:63"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Love will be extremely free in its choice. Your youngeſt Siſter has Charms, and I know not what, which you have not. A Maiden capable of ſo black and ſo criminal a deſign as is that you have brewed againſt me does not merit my eſteem. Live for ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who ſhall have as wicked a ſoul as you have a baſe one. Take again from this clumſey, though barbarous, wretch, a Ring which he has not gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it will reproach you eternally with your perfidiouſneſs. Adieu.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This generous Conquerour of himſelf, who apprehended ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extremity, and who beſides found not any Charms in the Court of <hi>Portugal,</hi> went a walking upon the Port; where having learnt that there was a <hi>Bark</hi> which weighed Anchor for <hi>Marſeiles,</hi> he went on Board after having written a Letter
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151646:63"/>of Thanks and Excuſes for what had paſſed to <hi>Don Alphonſo,</hi> whom he thought not convenient to ſee, that ſo he might not be obliged to acquaint him with the enraged ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of his Siſter.</p>
            <p>He ſtay'd not long at <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> but departed for <hi>Turin,</hi> where he went immediately after his Arrival to make his Compliments to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Royal, who let him know that ſhe had been acquainted with the adventure of <hi>Genoa.</hi> Then it was that our Illuſtrious Traveſty being weary of the world, tired with act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo many different parts, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly inſpired to return to God, and to her ſelf, gave the Hiſtory of her Life to the Princeſs, whoſe pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhe conjured to favour the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign ſhe had of finiſhing her days in a Cloiſter. Then it was that this Auguſt Princeſs ſhed tears for joy upon the return of this lovely
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151646:64"/>perſon, as the Angels of Peace up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Converſion of a ſinner; and that ſhe made her ſenſible of the effects of her goodneſs and her truly Royal Compaſſion. For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cauſed her to be attired con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formably to her Sex, and ſutably to her Condition, ſhe propoſed to her to enter into a famous Nunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of her nomination. <hi>Placidia</hi> teſtified all imaginable gratitude to Madam Royal, and acquainted her with the inclination ſhe had for another Houſe of Religiouſes, where ſhe had often aſſiſted at Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice at the time of her abode at <hi>Genoa.</hi> This Auguſt Princeſs very far from oppoſing her choice, gave her Letters written with her own hand for the Abbeſs of the Place; to whom her Highneſs recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her, as if ſhe had been her own Daughter, even to the engaging to furniſh her apartment. <hi>Placidia,</hi>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:151646:64"/>bleſſed with ſuch favourable Letters, was received with an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and univerſal joy by the Abbeſs and the Community, who look'd upon her as a perſon of a peculiar merit. A ſtrong reaſon had moved her to chuſe this Sanctuary; ſhe had learnt that the Daughter of the Magiſtrate, whom ſhe had played upon by her diſguiſe was there in the rank of Novices, that ſhe had long demanded to make her vows, and that ſhe could not have the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty granted her without a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Nullity of Marriage, or without certain Conjectures of the Death of her Husband; poſſeſſed with the thought that ſhe ſhould free her out of pains, ſhe made choice of that place, where ſhe took the Veil, and declared fifteen days before her profeſſion, what ſhe had been in regard of the poor <hi>Schola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtica,</hi> who had miſtaken her till
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:151646:65"/>then, that ſhe hugg'd her with tranſports of joy, that are not to be expreſſed. She was the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of her Sacrifice, as ſhe is, at preſent, the Emulatrice of her Vertues.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
